Guide to the Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims and Henry Ward Beecher collection, 1819-1980 ARC.212
Brooklyn Historical Society
During and after the Civil War, the city of Brooklyn prospered. Increased trade and population growth resulted in further expansion and a solid middle class presence. Meanwhile, Brooklyn's wealthy families molded the city into a flourishing metropolis complete with the cultural institutions enjoyed by the middle and upper classes, including the Brooklyn Academy of Music (1861), The Long Island Historical Society (1863), and the Brooklyn Club (circa 1865).
In 1880, the city of Brooklyn was the fourth largest producer of manufactured goods in the United States and was still expanding in population and commercial growth. Over the next forty years, the demographics of Brooklyn altered dramatically: a second mass wave of immigration increased the population still further, the Brooklyn and Manhattan Bridges opened in 1883 and 1909, the subway arrived in 1908, industrial complexes grew, Brooklyn was annexed into the city of New York in 1898, and public utilities were expanded into the borough. The middle and upper class residents of Brooklyn Heights, once the primary constituency of Plymouth Church and Church of the Pilgrims, began to move away from the commercial center of the city. By the 1920s, the once grand homes of Brooklyn's elite families had been converted into apartment houses and housed a population of clerks and secretaries who worked across the river in the Manhattan financial district. The Great Depression and development projects such as the Brooklyn-Queens Expressway led much of old Brooklyn Heights to fall into neglect until the early 1950s, when urban pioneers began to redevelop the neighborhood and promote its preservation.
The Borough of Brooklyn in 1999 was the most populous of New York City. The neighborhood along the bluffs overlooking the East River, Brooklyn Heights, was designated the first Historic District in New York City in 1966. Despite changes in population, politics, and economics, many of the 19th century brownstones, churches, and other structures still stand as testimony to the rich history of old Brooklyn.
Index to Henry Ward Beecher Sermons and Speeches
Following is an index of the Beecher sermons and other remarks in the collection, ordered alphabetically by title. Following the title is the date delivered (if known) and the box number-folder number (B-F) in which the piece can be found.
Activity (undated) B6-F8
Activity Indispensable to Normal Development (undated) B6-F9
The Administration of Wealth (undated) B6-F8
American Missionary Association (undated) B6-F9
American Missionary Association (undated) B6-F9
Be Conspicuous for Good Qualities (undated) B6-F6
The Bible (March 26, 1980) B3-F11
The Camp and Country (October 1861) B2-F3
Caution Against Procrastination (undated) B6-F6
Children of God Not to Crawl in His Presence (undated) B6-F6
Christ's Personal Ministry (undated) B6-F6
Church Worship (April 8, 1877) B3-F9
A Circuit of the Continent (November 29, 1883) B3-F17
Cleveland Letters (August 30 and September 8, 1866) B2-F9
Comfort in Knowing the Worst (undated) B6-F9
Commercial Wisdom of Religion (undated) B6-F6
Consolation in Trouble (March 3, 1876) B3-F10
Deterioration of Man (undated) B6-F7
Disenchantment of Scripture Passages (undated) B6-F6
Disinterested Benevolence (undated) B6-F8
The Divine Government (undated) B6-F6
Education of the Citizen (1860-1863) B2-F4
England and the Civil War of America (June 7, 1861) B2-F13
Eulogy on General Grant (October 22, 1885) Box 5 (no folder)
Eve of Emancipation (December 31, 1863) B2-F13
Extract from Lecture Room Talk (March 27, 1863) B2-F13
The Faults of Character (undated) B6-F9
Fruitfulness of the Human Mind (undated) B6-F8
Generosity and Benevolence (undated) B6-F8
Getting up in the Morning (undated) B6-F2
God's Love and Presence (February 23, 1868) B2-F13
God's Seal and Testimony (1858) B1-F36
Happiness (1870-1871) B2-F14
Heirship with Christ (February 14, 1886) B5-F6
Henry Ward Beecher in the West (1877) B3-F8
The Hidden Manna and the White Stone (July 1, 1866) B2-F9
The Higher Christian Life (February 16, 1872) B3-F10
The Household (1869-1871) B2-F12
How to Labor for a Revival (undated) B6-F6
The Human Body a Temple of the Holy Ghost (undated) B6-F8
Humanity (February 28, 1866) B5-F6
Inspiration of Scripture No. 1 (October 27, 1878) B3-F10
Interpolation of the Scriptures (undated) B6-F6
Is There a Devil? (February 25, 1883) B3-F17
The Kingdom of Heaven (January 3, 1886) B5-F6
A Knowledge of Doctrines Useful but Not Indispensable (undated) B6-F7
The Law of Human Development (undated) B6-F8
The Law of Sympathy (1858-1859) B2-F1
Laws and their Penalties (undated) B6-F7
Lecture (December 1, 1859) B2-F1
Lecture Room Talk (January 1, 1863?) B2-F13
Lecture Room Talk (May 21, 1875) B3-F10
Lecture Room Talk (July 27, 1876) B3-F10
Lecture Room Talk (March 1, 1878) B3-F10
Lecture Room Talk: excerpt (December 29, 1876) B3-F10
The Lord's Prayer No.2 (January 17, 1865) B2-F6
The Lord's Prayer No.3 (undated) B6-F13
Love for Southerners as well as Northerners (January 9, 1863) B2-F13
The Love of Money (undated) B6-F9
Lying Never Justifiable (undated) B6-F6
Men's Plans in Life (undated) B6-F9
Misconception of One's Duty as a Christian (June 15, 1877) B3-F10
Mission of Christ (undated) B6-F9
Money and Manhood: incomplete copy (1872-1873) B3-F2
Motives for Action (undated) B6-F7
Narrative on Trip to Ft. Sumter (April 12, 1865) Box 3 (no folder)
Natural Laws Moral, and Moral Laws Natural (undated) B6-F9
Old and New Ideas of Inspiration (undated) B6-F6
Origin of the Bible (undated) B6-F6
Patience (undated) B6-F9
Patient Waiting (April 16, 1865) Box 3 (no folder)
Patient Waiting (undated) B6-F9
Personal Influence (undated) B6-F7
Plymouth Church as a Pioneer in the Anti-Slavery Cause (May 25, 1870) B3-F10
Premonitions of God's Coming (1865) B2-F13
Professions of Faith (July 11, 1880) B3-F12
The Progress of Thought in the Church (in North American Review) (August 1882) B3-F14
Ready to Depart (December 31, 1863) B2-F13
Regular Progress in the Gospel Representation of Christ's Life (undated) B6-F6
Reign of the Common People (May 13, 1879) B3-F9
Remarks at 1st Anniversary of Equal Rights Association (May 10, 1867) B2-F10
Remote and Permanent Results (undated) B6-F8
Retrospection (undated) B6-F6
Riches (February 18, 1883) B3-F17
Self- Government (undated) B6-F9
Sepulcher in the Garden (March 26, 1880) B3-F11
Paul and Silas in the Prison of Thyatira (September 20, 1873) B2-F3
Sermon: 1st Corinthians 1:28 (November 19, 1872) B3-F1
Sermon: 1st Corinthians 2:15 (October 1868) B2-F11
Sermon: Acts of the Apostles 16 (undated) B6-F9
Sermon: Deut 6:1, 6-12 (July 2, 1884) B4-F1
Sermon: Genesis 9:11-16 (December 7, 1865) B2-F8
Sermon: Hebrews 4:9 (October 11, 1874) B3-F6
Sermon: Isa 16:3 (November 28, 1869) B2-F13
Sermon: James (?) 46:5 (June 28, 1885) B5-F2
Sermon: John 11:44 (July 5, 1885) B5-F3
Sermon: Matthew 11: 1-12 (November 9, 1884) B4-F2
Sermon: Mathew 25:26 (December 19, 1875) B3-F7
Sermon: Romans 2:4,5 (undated) B6-F3
Sermon: Romans 8:14,16 (undated) B6-F8
Sermon: Romans 8:19-23 (June 14, 1885) B5-F1
Sermon extract (May 31, 1874) B3-F10
Sermon extract (February 28, 1875) B3-F10
Sermon extract (March 19, 1876) B3-F10
Sermon extract (April 15, 1877) B3-F10
Sermon extract (April 14, 1878) B3-F10
Sermon notes: Ephesians 4: 31-32 (December 28, 1873) B3-F4
Sermon notes: Hebrews 12:18 and Galatians 5:22 (undated) B6-F14
Sermon notes: Luke 14:10 (June 22, 1877) B3-F9
Sermon notes: Luke 16:4 (undated) B6-F2
Sermon: Peter 2:17 (January 17, 1864) B2-F5
Sermon notes: Phil 1:15-18 (February 21, 1886) B5-F5
Sermon notes: Romans 14:12 (undated) B6-F2
Sermons (Sepember 1882-March 1883) B3-F16
Sermons (April-October 1883) Box 4 (no folder)
Sermons (October 1883-April 1884) Box 4 (no folder)
Sermons (April-October 1884) Box 5 (no folder)
Sermons (October 5-November 2, 1884) Box 5 (no folder)
Sermons (1885-1886) Box 5 (no folder)
Sermons (1886-1887) Box 5 (no folder)
Sermons: printed (circa 1887) B6-F1
Shame (undated) B6-F6
Significance of the Term Hatred as Used by Christ (January 10, 1886) B5-F4
Signification of the Word 'Forty' in the Scriptures (undated) B6-F6
Sorrow and Its Dangers (undated) B6-F9
Thanksgiving Sermon (November 27, 1879) B3-F10
The Threefold Man (undated) B6-F7
Truths of Law Founded in Nature (undated) B6-F6
Two Hundred and Forty Years Ago! (undated) B6-F4
Unconscious Selfishness (undated) B6-F9
The Unity of Christians by the Power of Love (July 11, 1886) B5-F6
Upper and Under (circa 1874) B3-F5
A Voice (undated) B6-F9
The Vulgarity of Ignorance (undated) B6-F6
Wants of Young Men (May 6, 1860) B2-F2
What Men Believe Religion Can Do For Them (undated) B6-F6
Works (undated) B6-F8
The Worth of Man (January 1882) B3-F13
Young America (undated) B6-F5
Plymouth chimes (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Scrapbooks; Clippings (information artifacts); Photographs; Cartes-de-visite (card photographs); Sermons; Antislavery movements |z United States; Sunday schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; United States |x Religion; Picture postcards; Pews and pew rights; Reformers |z United States; Religious education of children |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Typescripts; Correspondence; Congregational churches |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Clergy; Cylinder phonographs (phonographs); Authors, American; Congregationalists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn Heights (New York, N.Y.); Religious institutions |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Church newsletters; City clergy |z New York (State) |z New York; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Church history; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Religious life and customs; Lectures and lecturing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Clergy as authors; Adultery |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Trials (Adultery) |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Abolitionists |z New York (State); Beecher, Henry Ward, Mrs.; Abbott, Lyman; Durkee, J. Stanley (James Stanley); Beecher, William Constantine -- Correspondence; Beecher, Henry Ward; Hunt, Rose Ward; Hillis, Newell Dwight; Hibben, Paxton; Fifield, Lawrence Wendell; Tilton, Theodore; Tilton, Elizabeth M. Richards; Plymouth Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Church of the Pilgrims (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Church of the Pilgrims (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.). Sunday School; Plymouth Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.). Sunday School; Henry Ward Beecher Literary and Debating Society (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Henry Ward Beecher Missionary Circle (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Bethel of Plymouth Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Plymouth Institute (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Series 1: Henry Ward Beecher, 1819-1958; 2050; 16.5 Cubic Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes material that pertains directly to Henry Ward Beecher, his career at and relations with Plymouth Church, and his public and private life. The series opens with both personal and business correspondence, both to and from Beecher. Topics of the correspondence range from Beecher's political stance, to the upkeep of his summer home in Peekskill, N.Y., to the sincerity of one of his product endorsements. Also included within the correspondence section of the series is a copy of Beecher's letter of acceptance of the pastorate at Plymouth Church.
  The series includes a section of miscellaneous personal materials relating to Beecher, such as a scrapbook of his final journey to England and a stock certificate, as well as materials pertaining to other members of the Beecher family, including his wife Eunice White Bullard, his sister Harriet Beecher Stowe, and his son William. As a whole, the section of personal and familial papers is primarily made up of correspondence and newspaper clippings. Beecher's sermons, lectures, and publications in both manuscript and print form also form a substantial portion of the series. These include both hand-written manuscripts and typescripts made and compiled by Beecher's stenographer, T. J. Ellinwood.
  Beecher's various activities and aspects of his career are well-documented in the series. A few items pertaining to Beecher's tenure in Indianapolis are in the series, including newspaper clippings, reminiscences, and the hundredth anniversary program of the Second Presbyterian Church where he served as pastor. Material on Beecher's anti-slavery activities includes documents relaying Plymouth's position on slavery, materials relating to "Pinky" (an enslaved girl who Beecher "auctioned" at Plymouth), and a scrapbook containing newspaper clippings and correspondence regarding Beecher's position on slavery, especially expressing opposition to Beecher's stance (box 41). Included here is an audio cylinder with brief remarks from Rose Ward Hunt (Pinky) on the occasion of her return to Plymouth Church in 1927; a digital version of the cylinder recording can be heard in the library. Newspaper accounts of Beecher's activities generally at Plymouth Church are in the series, including material relating to Church events centered around Beecher, such as his "Silver Wedding" Celebration. Beecher's political involvement is reflected in the correspondence of major figures of the day, newspaper clippings relating to Beecher and Lincoln, reactions to Lincoln's assassination, and a memento of General U.S. Grant.
  The Beecher-Tilton adultery trial is well documented through contemporary newspaper clippings, the published proceedings of the trial, and pamphlets regarding the trial. Also included in this section is an invitation to visit the Tiltons on their tenth anniversary. A section of the series concerning Beecher's death contains a number of memorials to Beecher, including poetry, memorial booklets, his eulogy, scrapbooks, and photographs. Also found here are artifacts from his funeral and a hand-calligraphed album commemorating the pastor. The series closes with a section on Beecher memorials, containing information regarding several of the organizations founded in Beecher's name following his death, memorial magazines, a Brooklyn City memorial proclamation made in 1958, and reminiscences of friends and congregants, including Irene Ovington's 1895 memories of Beecher with a reference to the Underground Railroad.
  Arrangement
  The series is organized in ten sections:
  Section 1: Correspondence, Personal and Business (1847-1887)
  Section 2: Personal and Familial Papers (1845-1975)
  Section 3: Sermons, Lectures, and Publications (1848-1904)
  Section 4: Beecher in Indianapolis (1913-1938)
  Section 5: Beecher and Plymouth Church (1860-1885)
  Section 6: Beecher's Involvement in the Anti-Slavery Movement (1819-1959)
  Section 7: Political Climate (1834-1937)
  Section 8: Beecher-Tilton Trial (1873-1934)
  Section 9: Death (1887-1891)
  Section 10: Memorials (1871-1958)
  In section 3, the container list indicates which materials are in handwritten, typescript, or print form. Typescripts and printed matter explicitly attributable to T.J. Ellinwood are indicated with the initals TJE.
  - Section 1a: Correspondence, Personal, 2051
    - Beecher to Tilton re: experiences in Britain., 1863; 2053 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - To Charles re: his political position., 1866; 2054 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - To Mr. Rodgers., 1865-1867; 2055 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - To caretakers of summer house, Mr. and Mrs. Fred D. Chandler., 1881-1887; 2056 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Letter from HWB on letterhead., 1885; 2057 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - To Mrs. Beach., undated; 2058 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Section 1b: Correspondence, Business, 2059
    - Letter of acceptance to Plymouth (photo reproduction)., 1847; 2060 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - To Cushing family re: baptism., 1849; 2061 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Letter to lozenge company exalting product and newspaper reprint (October 15)., 1858; 2062 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - re: Plymouth Church organist., 1878; 2063 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - From G.E. Sawyer re: donation to church., 1884; 2064 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - To Mayor Whitney: declining public reception in his honor., 1886; 2065 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - re: Pear's soap endorsement, original and reply., 1886; 2066 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous: printed in newspapers., 1878-1886; 2067 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Section 2: Personal and Familial Papers, 2068
    - Beecher's stock certificate for Continental Insurance Co., 1867; 2069 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Trip to England: departure ceremony- tickets, invitation, itinerary, lecture announcements., 1886; 2070 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - New York news clippings reporting on trip., 1886; 2071 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - British news clippings reporting on trip., 1886; 2072 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - United States papers reporting on trip., 1886; 2073 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - British and other foreign papers reporting on trip., 1886; 2074 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence re: Charles and James C. Beecher., 1857, 1942; 2075 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Family autographs/ notes: Lyman Beecher, Edward, Thomas, Charles, William, and Henry Beecher., 1845-1891; 2076 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Mrs. John Tasker Howard to Mr. Howard re: daughter's conversion and relationship with the Stowes: annotated transcription., 1858; 2077 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Edward Beecher: golden wedding anniversary, newspaper clippings, obituary., 1862, 1893-1895; 2078 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - William C. Beecher: business letter, letter to Durkee (pastor of Plymouth)., 1881, 1927; 2079 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence from Eunice Beecher; incl. autograph book., 1886-1896; 2080 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - 2 letters from Eunice Beecher., 1891; 2081 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Eunice Beecher: newspaper clippings., 1897; 2082 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Letter from Hattie B. Beecher (wife of HWB Jr.)., 1898; 2083 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Harriet Beecher Stowe: articles, newsclippings, brochure from house tour., circa 1896-1975; 2084 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Dr. John Beecher: newsclipping about "Walk for Peace"., 1961; 2085 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Family scrapbook pages: newsclippings, images., circa 1880-1911; 2086 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Family tree: beginning with Henry Ward Beecher., circa 1940; 2087 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - John Greenleaf Whittier writing sample., undated; 2088 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Mrs. Oliver Coomes: 2 Brooklyn Sanitary Fair tickets, cards relating to Coomes incl. calling card., 1868; 2089 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - The Christian World (British) reporting on trip., 1886; 2090 (Box 30, Item 1)
    - Scrapbook of newsclippings re: HWB and family., 1887-1907; 2091 (Box 31, Item 1)
    - William C. Beecher Letterbook., 1864-1869; 2092 (Box 32, Item 1)
    - Scrapbook: clippings on Beecher., 1866-1876; 2093 (Box 33, Item 1)
    - Scrapbook: clippings on Beecher., 1877; 2094 (Box 34, Item 1)
    - Scrapbook of political news., 1880; 2095 (Box 35, Item 1)
    - Scrapbook: clippings on Beecher., 1883-1884; 2099 (Box 36, Item 1)
    - Scrapbook: clippings on Beecher., 1885-1886; 2100 (Box 37, Item 1)
    - Scrapbook of trip kept by Maj. Pond, Beecher's agent., 1886; 2101 (Box 38, Item 1)
    - Scrapbook: Beecher, family and church., 1852, 1860-1879; 2102 (Box 39, Item 1)
    - Scrapbook: clippings on Beecher., 1885-1916; 2103 (Box 66, Item 1)
  - Section 3: Sermons, Lectures, and Publications., 2104
    General
    The description indicates which materials are in handwritten, typescript, or print form. Typescripts and printed matter explicitly attributable to T.J. Ellinwood are indicated with the initals TJE.
    - "God's Seal and Testimony" (print)., 1858; 3457 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - "The Law of Sympathy" and lecture excerpt (handwritten)., 1859; 2106 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - "Wants of Young Men" (May 6) (TJE, typescript)., 1860; 2107 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - "The Camp and Country" (October) (handwritten)., 1861; 2108 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - "Education of the Citizen" (handwritten)., circa 1860-1863; 2109 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Sermon (January 17) (typescript)., 1864; 2783 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - "The Lord's Prayer" (January 17) (typescript)., 1865; 2111 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Sermon (December 7) (typescript)., 1865; 2113 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "The Hidden Manna and the White Stone" and "The Cleveland Letters" (TJE, printed, circa 1892)., 1866; 2114 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Speech delivered at American Equal Rights Association (May 10) (typescript)., 1867; 2115 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Sermon (October) (typescript)., 1868; 2116 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - "The Household" (handwritten)., 1869-1871; 2117 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Sermons (typescript)., 1860-1869; 2118 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - "Happiness" (handwritten)., 1870-1871; 2119 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - "Narrative on Trip to Ft. Sumter" (April 12) (TJE, typescript, 1892)., 1865; 2120 (Box 3, Item 1)
    - "Patient Waiting" (April 16) (TJE, typescript, 1892)., 1865; 2121 (Box 3, Item 2)
    - Corinthians 1:28 (November 19) (handwritten)., 1872; 2122 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - "Money and Manhood" (handwritten)., 1872-1873; 2123 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Paul and Silas in the Prison of Thyatria (September 20) (printed)., 1873; 2124 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Sermon notes for Ehesians 4:31-32 (December 28) (handwritten)., 1873; 2125 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - "Upper and Under" (handwritten)., circa 1874; 2126 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Hebrews 4:9 (handwritten) (October 11)., 1874; 2127 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Matthew 25:26 (December 19) (handwritten)., 1875; 2128 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - "Henry Ward Beecher in the West" (printed)., 1877; 2129 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Sermon notes for Luke 14:10 (Self-seeking): including set given to James Higgins by Beecher (June 22) (handwritten)., 1877; 2130 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Sermons and Talks (handwritten and typescripts)., 1870-1879; 2131 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - "The Bible" and "Sepulcher in the Garden" (March 26) (typescripts)., 1880; 2132 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Titus 2: 7-15 "Profession of Faith" (July 11) (handwritten)., 1880; 2133 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - "The Worth of Man" (January 1882; February 18, 1883) (typescript)., 1882, 1883; 2134 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - "Progress of Thought in the Church"(printed in August North American Review.) Beecher's statement on evolution., 1882; 2135 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - "Statement Before the Congressional Association," including Beecher's resignation from the Association resulting from his views on evolution. (October 13) (printed)., 1882; 2136 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Sermons (2 bound copies) (September-March) (TJE, printed, 1892)., 1882-1883; 2137 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Sermons (typescripts and printed)., 1883; 2138 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Sermons (2 bound copies) (April-October) (TJE, printed, 1892)., 1883; 2139 (Box 4, Item 1)
    - Sermons (2 bound copies) (October-April) (TJE, printed, 1892)., 1883-1884; 2140 (Box 4, Item 2)
    - Sermon: Deuteronomy 6:1, 6-12 (July 2) (handwritten)., 1884; 2141 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Sermon (typescripts)., 1884; 2142 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Sermons (2 copies) (April-October) (TJE, printed, 1892)., 1884; 2143 (Box 5, Item 1-2)
    - Sermons (2 copies) (October-November) (TJE, printed, 1892)., 1884; 2144 (Box 5, Item 3-4)
    - Sermon: Romans 8:19-23 (June 14) (handwritten)., 1885; 2145 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Sermon: James 46:5 (June 28) (handwritten)., 1885; 2146 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Sermon: John 11:44 (July 5) (handwritten)., 1885; 2147 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - "Eulogy on General Grant" (October 22) (handwritten)., 1885; 2148 (Box 5, Item 5)
    - Sermons (TJE, printed, 1892)., 1885-1886; 2149 (Box 5, Item 6)
    - "Significance of the Term Hatred as Used by Christ" (January 10) (handwritten)., 1886; 2150 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Sermon Notes for Philistines 1: 15-18 (February 21) (handwritten)., 1886; 2151 (Box 5, Folder 5)